And right now we're going to kick off
with Neil Ford. Neil Ford, a
distinguished engineer at ThoughtWorks.
And one of the big things that we very
often forget about when we uh when we
use AI coding assistants and coding
agents is the long-term maintenance, the
long-term debt that we really add in
when we when we are, you know, rapidly
building with AI. And so Neil's going to
give us a great insight into fitness
functions uh or fitness functiondriven
architecture and making sure we think
about the longerterm design, the
longerterm architecture of the
applications that we build. So with
that, Neil, it's a pleasure to welcome
you to Native DevCon.
>> Thank you very much. Thanks for having
me. So, uh, I'm going to talk about the
looming disaster of code quality and
sustainable software a little bit, but
mostly what I'm going to do is tie
together a bunch of things that exist
out in the world. Uh, so let's first
start talking about this concept of an
architectural fitness function. This is
something we defined in the book
building evolution architectures
originally back in 2017. And this is
sort of like a unit test but for
architecture capabilities.
Uh we want to verify that as we build
our architecture that we don't break
stuff. And so our definition is any
mechanism that gives you an objective
integrity assessment on some
architecture characteristic. But that's
how these are different than something
like fitness functions or than unit test
because these have a much broader scope.
Software metrics for example. I will
actually give you my preferred metric
for detecting AI slop in your codebase
from an architecture standpoint a little
bit later in this talk. Code level
metrics let you assess things about your
architecture. Unit testing libraries
which I'll talk about that are
specialized for this. But we also use
things like monitors and observability.
These are all things that we need to
know about architecture because
architecture is not just our codebase.
It's also data and uh um
integration architecture and all the
other things that go into our
ecosystems. Chaos engineering is a
perfect example of this idea of an
architectural fitness function. And over
time we've seen more and more of these
mechanisms come about and I'll show you
how that applies in the real world uh
kind of scenarios. The second part of
this is it needs to have an objective
integrity check. So that's the way you
verify something is you come up with an
objective value for it and then it's
either true or false or it's a number or
so that's how we verify things. And we
also look at not just code but also
things that impact architecture like
data. If we're in a distributed
architecture and splitting data, we
would still like to have referential
integrity between our databases. That's
an architectural concern. if we're in a
distributed architecture. And so it's
broader than just code bases.
I typically at this point want to show
you a very simple example of one of
these things. Uh but this one is
particularly apt
cyclic dependencies.
If I'm writing a software system that
composes of components and most of them
if they're any complexity have
components in them, one of the things I
want to try to avoid are cyclic
dependencies.
That's where one component references
another component which refers a third
one which references the original one.
Again, the reason this is bad is because
now if I reuse one of these components,
I have to take the whole rat's nest with
me. And if one of these is also
cyclically bound up with another one,
then now I'm having to pull this entire
uh tree of relationships. If I try to
reuse something, this is generally
considered an antiattern in software
architecture.
But it's subtle because if I have one of
these in my codebase, it's not a big
deal. If I have a hundred of these in my
codebase, my codebase is a piece of
trash. And so there's a a tipping point
here somewhere where it gets bad enough
to become really bad. The problem though
is that developers as they're coding
along and their IDE pops up a dialogue
and says, "You want me to autoimp import
that for you?" They never read that
dialogue. They just swat it away and
keep doing what they're doing. Most of
the time it's okay, every once in a
while it's this. And even worse, unless
you explicitly tell your agent, don't do
this. It's going to do this all the time
because it doesn't know that this is not
something you should be doing. This is
just something that it wants to do. How
do you prevent this from happening?
Because I can't spend all of my day
going through every line of code that's
been created to make sure nobody's
created cycles in my codebase. You
create an architectural fitness function
for this. This is using the tool called
ArcUnit that understands dependencies
and code bases. I wire this into my
continuous build and whether I write
this code or another human writes this
code or machine writes this code, I
don't get cycles in my codebase anymore.
This is a way that I can create more
sustainable code bases by building guard
rails around the important parts of my
architecture that I want to preserve for
long periods of time. Fortunately, there
are a lot of tools and frameworks that
have come out in this space. ArcUnit is
a library in the Java world. That's the
code I just showed you is ArcUnit, but
there are also a couple in the net
world. This is ArcUnit Net and Net Arc
test, both of which work in the .NET
world. Here is Piest Arc, which is from
the u uh Python world. This is ArcUnit
TS in the TypeScript, JavaScript,
ECMAScript world. And here is Arc Go in
the Go language world. And so pretty
much all the platforms, technologies,
and frameworks you can think about have
tools that let you write these
architectural fitness functions to
validate that the architectural concerns
in your code are actually working
correctly.
Okay, that's fine and good, but
limiting
[snorts] because here's the thing I
really want to write a fitness function
for.
I have microservices.
I have an orchestrator order placement,
payment, and inventory. And the way I've
designed my architecture, I don't want
the domain services talking to each
other because the orchestrators holding
on to the state of my workflow. And if
they talk to one another, my state gets
out of whack and bad things happen.
Where can I write my arcunit fitness
function to validate that that the
domain services only communicate with
the orchestrator? Where's the tool or
the framework or library I can download
to do that?
Unfortunately, that does not exist
nor can it exist.
The problem when you get into
architecture is variability.
What have I written these things in?
This is microservices. These may all be
written in different platforms or
technology stacks. So, who knows what
these things are written in? How are
they communicating with each other? Is
it REST? Is it SOAP? Is it message cues?
Is it gRPC? what kind of database are
they? It's it's so many variables.
There's no way you can find a pre-built
framework to do this for you. And so a
lot of architects just look at this and
just give up hope. But that's the wrong
approach to
the book that we're writing right now is
a book called architecture as code which
is encouraging architects to treat their
software development ecosystem as if it
were a codebase. And one of the mantras
in our book is what data do I need and
where does that data live?
So if I ask this question about this
particular problem,
what data do I need? Well, I need to
know who these domain services are
talking to. Where does that data live?
It lives in log files that they can
produce. And I can guarantee that they
produce. And so my fitness function
looks like this. for each one of those
services. Import the logs for the last
24 hours. And unless they're calling the
orchestrator, they're cheating. Yell at
them. They violated my fitness function.
[snorts]
This is actually written in Ruby, which
is one of my favorite little scripting
languages. And in fact, most of these
architecture fitness functions are not
written in the platform or technology
stack that you're implementing your
solution in. and they're written in
little tiny scripting languages that
aggregate data that's already laying
around in your ecosystem that you're
just not taking advantage of. Uh most of
these fitness functions are 10 or 15
lines of code that's just piecing
together some things that are already
there. So what we're doing in
architecture is code is looking at all
the ways that architecture intersects
with the software development ecosystem
and trying to define those intersections
with fitness functions. Architecture and
implementation is obvious because we
have to implement architecture in code
to actually make it work. But we all can
look at architecture and engineering
practices.
One of the problems we perpetually have
is I need to make a bad choice. I've got
to choose between a monor repo or repo
per service. And the problem is they
both suck, but they both suck in
different ways.
Using this, you can find a way to write
code that mitigates the negative side
effects of the choices you have to make.
Anyway, that's [snorts] an example of
engineering practices. You can build
intersections around things like team
topologies or integration architecture
or the enterprise, which I'll talk about
in more depth in just a second. And
[snorts] of course, generative AI and
infrastructure and data and things like
the business environment. And in fact,
let's look at an example of this this
intersection with data and architecture.
The architect says, "I've decided to
split the database into two domain
databases for better fault tolerance,
better change control, and better
scalability."
The product owner says,"Great, but make
sure we don't lose any trouble tickets
that both domains have the same tickets.
Where is this information documented? I
just recently did a workshop and the
universal answer to this question was in
some spreadsheet somewhere." And alas,
that is probably true. Some spreadsheet
somewhere holds on to this information.
But how are we verifying that?
So here's the scenario. I have customers
and I have tickets and I've had to split
the database apart for architectural
reasons because I want better fault
tolerance and scalability.
[snorts] But now I need to make sure
that all the tickets have corresponding
customers because I don't want to have
tickets without a customer. That doesn't
make sense. So what data do I need and
where does it live?
What I'm going to do is go to this
database and grab the set of customer
keys from there. Go to my ticket
database and grab the ticket foreign
customer keys there. And [snorts] when
my Q has no messages pending, in other
words, it is at rest, assert that TC is
a member of C. In other words, assert
that there are no tickets in that
database that do not exist in this
database. I am now verifying the
referential integrity between these two
databases as if it were a single
database but doing it at the
architecture level because I need a
distributed architecture. This is an
example of the data intersection of
architecture as code and this works
great. We've done this a lot. Problem is
it's hard to do at an enterprise scale.
So this works fantastic. We've been
doing this for years at the uh
application level.
But now I want to talk about something
that I'm calling a meta bounded context.
When we talk about software
architecture, we talk about bounded
context all the time as it pertains to
the domain that we're writing. But
projects
have a meta bounded context which is the
way they've implemented well stuff like
this highly specific to this project
because I have details about the
databases that are used in this project
that I'm implementing for this fitness
function.
Hold on to that thought for just a
second because now I want to touch on
this intersection of architecture and
the enterprise.
We have a defined role called enterprise
architect who does this intersection
with architecture and enterprise. And in
fact there are a bunch of different
things that enterprise architects end up
doing in terms of software architecture
including things like global governance
uh um global code quality governance.
That's what I'm after here. This, by the
way, normalize distance from the main
sequence. If you're looking for one
single metric that identifies AI slop in
your codebase,
that's it. It looks for code that has
been built by brute force with a lack of
abstraction and too much implementation
details. Scores poorly on normalized
distance from the main sequence. So just
buy what by the way if you're looking
for actual metrics that find AI
generated code that's it and this is the
only thing that we've really seen a lot
of success with because as a group of
enterprise architects I would like to
govern a lot of stuff in my ecosystem
but this is really the only kind of
stuff we found that is universally
useful these kind of holistic governance
uh code quality things like cyclatic
complexity No code base benefits from
having overly complex code or poorly
structured code. But the problem we've
run into is we'd like to be a lot more
hands-on. In fact, our largest global
client has within their enterprise
architecture group a role called an
evolutionary architect and they are
going around implementing fitness
functions within their ecosystem to try
to govern things from the enterprise
level.
But there's a problem with that. We've
been doing this since 2017 2018 and
we've discovered the issues with that
that fortunately Agentic AI has come to
the rescue for. So let's talk for a
second about architecture and Agentic AI
and MCP. Before MCP, if I wanted to call
something directly, I had to know
exactly what that API was and know the
details and the metadata and the format.
MCP is like the best ever integration
hub because it gives you a way to query
capabilities or tools, etc., and allows
you to wire things together in a much
more generic way because you can query
capabilities and come back and iterate
on those capabilities and do things on
behalf of them. the MCP primitives which
I'm sure you're familiar with tools that
are tools that are available that you
can call and do stuff for like database
calls u resources like uh logs file
contents this is where I get logs very
often when I'm doing those kinds of
compare logs in my fitness functions I
can do that through something like MCP
because log contents are one of the
things it can deliver and of course
prompt libraries to let you piece things
together within that uh that MC MCP kind
of universe. So let's talk about how
this solves
this problem.
As an enterprise architect,
I want to be able to write these kind of
fitness functions because I as an
enterprise architect want to guarantee
that the projects I have have
referential integrity between the
databases.
Here's the problem. is the meta bounded
context
because as an enterprise architect I'm
sitting way far away from that
application and if I write this code and
they change the implementation
it breaks and that's the fundamental
problem of trying to implement these far
distance fitness functions is
brutaleness
because to be able to do that I have to
pierce the metabounded context to get to
the implementation detail tails and that
makes it brittle and that reduces its
effectiveness because if these things
break a lot because of incidental
reasons you get frustrated with them and
go ah this is not worth the trouble
don't want to do that anymore
that's where MCP comes in
because enterprise architects can now
through the service mesh which is the
thing that generally executes all of
these things say I want to validate
referential integrity
The project itself can set up an MCP
server inside their metabounded context
that knows the details of how to do that
and can offer this as a tool for the
enterprise architects.
I [snorts] want you to validate
referential integrity. When it gets
that, it says, "Oh, well, I know what
that means. When Q is equal to zero,
assert that TC is an element of C."
But then when the implementation
changes, which it inevitably does, I
need to add experts over there who also
have tickets, who also have foreign key
relationships between things. Now the
implementation of my fitness function
has to change,
but the intent doesn't.
This is huge as an empowering for
enterprise architects to be able to
state intent like this at the
architecture level without having to
know the implementation details of how
things work and still be able to
implement this kind of holistic
governance across the entire
organization. This having MCP as this
ultimate sort of integration layer is
fantastic because now it separates the
intent from the implementation in a way
that's very very useful for enterprise
architects. So could not have come along
at a better time for us. And so mesh
architectures like service mesh plus
agentic capabilities plus fitness
functions is what we're calling uh
fitness functiondriven architecture or
alternatively very ambitiously 21st
century enterprise architecture because
that's really what we're after here
because what this allows us to do and
this is one other interesting use for AI
that's a sort of a bonus use here
as an architect.
I design a lot of stuff. I design
components around domains and
relationships and dependencies between
these components and put a lot of
thought into this as an architect. This
is what we do as an architect is figure
out coupling and cohesion around
components etc.
But then I hand this off to a group of
developers to implement it.
After it's implemented, I look at it
again and I go, "What? what
ticket assignment disappeared at some
point during the implementation and uh
customer registration's not there and
this new thing showed up that I never
designed as part of my architecture and
all this chaos has occurred and this is
actually what got implemented
despite my nice clean design when I
handed this to developers and schedule
pressure showed up and things changed
and I ended up implementing in chaos
like this. This idea of architecture as
code. What this allows us to do is
actually define things
as code.
Define our domains. Define the
relationships between them. This is our
architecture as code pseudo code. And
then assert that classes are only
contained within classes within those
domains. This is the other use that we
have found is quite useful for
generative AI. the second L in LLM
because you hand it this pseudo code and
tell it to produce me a fitness function
in Java ornet and it will do so and what
this is of course doing is validating
the directory structure. So you hand
this to an LLM and it will produce
concrete fitness functions for you. This
is nice because I can keep my rules in
pseudo code and then if I have a Java
codebase or Golang codebase orn net
codebase or python codebase I can
generate all of the uh the pertinent
fitness functions for those that
validate the structure as I write my
code. Just like a building architect
creates a plan for how the build of the
room should be laid out and the
relationships like where plumbing goes.
I can now as an architect define how I
want things put together in my
ecosystem. That is this idea of a
fitness function-driven architecture and
it's a way to enhance collaboration
between architects and developers to
make sure that they are building the
things that I actually want them to
build. This is what we were referring to
as fitness function-driven architecture
and it's similar to so fitness functions
are like unit tests in that it allows
you to verify things as we go along
preferably on each change and it makes
sure that we haven't broken anything
that we're building on.
Fitness functions are not like unit
tests in that failures are placeholders
for conversations about design
decisions.
As an architect, I build one of those
things that say, "Here are the
components I need." And then somebody
builds a new component.
That's not an error. That's a
placeholder for conversation.
I'm going to I don't want to yell at
them about it. I just want to know that
it happened. And so, architecture is
code is really a fast feedback framework
for anything that happened in
architecture that I care about, let me
know about it so that I can react to it.
Fitness function-driven architecture is
like test-driven development that we
both build things and constantly verify
them as we go along. It's unlike
test-driven development in that it is
the mechanics for evolutionary
architecture. It's not meant to cover
every detail, just the important stuff.
And this is really an important
perspective. We're not trying to create
an architecture police state here. We're
trying to create an ecosystem where we
can work within the context of a project
and define rules at the enterprise
architecture level that I really want to
implement but I don't want to get into
details of how to implement that.
Agentic AI is a really really nice way
to do that and it gives us a way to uh
build this kind of holistic governance
in a way that doesn't create this sort
of brittle breakage all the time. So
very very nice more and more details of
this coming out. In fact, we just
published an article about this on the
O'Reilly website um talking about these
details. So u much more of this coming
in the architectures code book which
should be out sometime later this next
year.
And that's it. 30 seconds to spare.
Thanks very much. [music]
Heat. Heat.